<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
	<title> - personal</title>
	<subtitle>Software Pie</subtitle>
	<link href="https://wayofthepie.github.io/tags/personal/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="https://wayofthepie.github.io"/>
	<generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
	<updated>2021-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	<id>https://wayofthepie.github.io/tags/personal/atom.xml</id>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Reflecting on my Software Career</title>
		<published>2021-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://wayofthepie.github.io/personal/reflecting-on-my-career-to-date/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://wayofthepie.github.io/personal/reflecting-on-my-career-to-date/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I started my software career in April 2011, in EMC, as an intern in the Build and Release Engineering team. Almost 10 years ago. For the first four years, I worked mostly on Operations, our internal build systems, and our production systems. There was a sprinkle of development scattered throughout those years. In 2015 our group started the journey towards a DevOps transformation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took us about a year and a half before all our devs were comfortable enough to continuously deploy to production. But it was an amazing transformation. We went from releases every 2 months in a giant, insanely architected system (more on that later), with separate Ops&#x2F;QA&#x2F;Dev teams, to 60+ releases a day with the team writing the software owning it to production and beyond. The new system was 100+ networked services, most folks did TDD, overall the quality of what we delivered and how delivered it was orders of magnitude better.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;continue-reading&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ll talk more about that group and my time there soon. I left EMC&#x2F;Dell in June 2018 and went to McKesson. My role there was similar but applied globally. The goal was to improve how developers created and delivered software, globally. Looking back, we did quite a lot to guide the company. I feel like I accomplished a lot in the 2 years, 7 months I was there. More on that later too.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I left McKesson in December 2020 and since then I&#x27;ve spent some time thinking about what my next career move will be. Before I do that, I want to reflect on the last 10 years in more depth. But even before that, why did I choose this career in the first place? &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What have I accomplished, both personally and with others? What insane things have I seen? Maybe then I might have better insight as to what I want to do next.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-computers&quot;&gt;Why Computers?&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my dreams as a kid, I shit you not, was to become an engineer and computer person (I did not know what a &amp;quot;Software Engineer&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;Developer&amp;quot; was back then&amp;quot;) so I could build an airship all by myself. Just like the airship &lt;em&gt;Invincible&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; from Final Fantasy IX. Then I could make it super high-tech, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; design and build the actual airship. Here is the best image I could find of that airship:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;invincible.webp&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
 &lt;figcaption&gt;Final Fantasy IX, Invincible airship.&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazing right! I couldn&#x27;t find a better image. Ten year old me was also very easily excited. I have, unfortunately, not managed to build an airship yet. Perhaps that will be a career move down the line. Only future me can answer that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;ok-back-on-track&quot;&gt;Ok, Back On Track&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to reality. We did not get a computer in our house until the early 2000s. I think I was 10 or 11. My cousin had two computers. One for the family, and another which was his own. We used to spend ages on his one, just seeing what we could do. It was a Windows 98 (or Windows ME 🤔) system. I&#x27;ll never forget discovering the terminal and the &lt;code&gt;tree&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; command. My initial thoughts were something along the lines of &amp;quot;Look mam! I&#x27;m a hacker!&amp;quot;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That PC was taken from a hotel his uncle worked at. And it contained a &lt;em&gt;tonne&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; of details about guests and the business. Being a kid, I thought nothing of this. Little did I know that this would be (and was) quite a theme in the tech world. It would also be something I&#x27;d come across time and time again in the future.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;pc-gaming&quot;&gt;PC Gaming&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we finally got our PC I was blown away! It was so cool. I could now play PC games! That was all I cared about at the time. But I think for a long time I wasn&#x27;t allowed to buy any. The first game I remember playing was &lt;em&gt;Command &amp;amp; Conquer: Generals&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. I had played &lt;em&gt;Command &amp;amp; Conquer: Red Alert&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; on the PSX, but this was a massive step up. The first game to truly blow me away was &lt;em&gt;Operation Flaspoint&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. I got this not long after its release. I think in 2003 sometime. The premise of an open warzone where you could drive tanks and fly helicopters to achieve your mission was mind-blowing to me at the time. The only issue with our PC was one  lot of folks with PCs must have had at the time. It was running &lt;em&gt;Windows ME&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; 😬. I can hear you offering your condolences. Thank you.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was around the time I started to play Flashpoint that I discovered &lt;em&gt;Adobe Photoshop&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. I don&#x27;t really remember why, but we had it installed on our PC, I opened it one day, and then I was hooked. I remember getting an image of the Tower of Babel and editing it until it looked as weird as I possibly could make it. I did this for a few months to a bunch of images until I was able to use the different tools pretty proficiently. We had dial-up at the time, so either the images were orders of magnitude less high quality than I remember, or we had huge internet bills over those months.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;tower-of-babel.jpg&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
 &lt;figcaption&gt;The Tower of Babel&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-photos-to-films&quot;&gt;From Photos To Films&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That lasted a few months. After that, I didn&#x27;t do much with computers until I was in my mid-teens. I still played games, but it was mostly on the PSX, and PS2 when that came out. When I was in fourth year, I think I was 15 at the time, our class entered a film competition. If I remember correctly, it was about the dangers of drinking. I was a bit wild back then and used to drink a lot anyway so I found it hilarious! But, I enjoyed that project. I was the editor, and it brought back the joy I had when using Photoshop a few years earlier.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t remember what editing software I was using, maybe Sony Vega. But I spent hours on that film. There is one scene I remember the most. It was the climax of the movie. One of the girls gets drunk and injures herself. The scene was at a party and was filmed as a timelapse. I played around a bit with how best to show the impact alcohol was having on her. The final version had five or six short time jumps from the start of the party to when she gets injured. With each jump to a new scene, the film slowed down a few fractions of a second. After two jumps it made the viewer feel uneasy, after three it was quite clear something bad was going on, the music became more ominous. This along with the great acting in that scene - I am imagining Oscar-worthy acting here - making it the best part of the film by far. In the climax of the overall scene, the girl falls over and breaks her arm or something - not sure exactly what - and it looked awesome in super slow motion.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this, I didn&#x27;t do much with computers again, until I thought I wanted to be a game developer and started a course in game design when I was 18.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;game-development-nah&quot;&gt;Game Development? Nah.&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I picked up guitar when I was 8. I used to do lessons with my sister, we would go to a teacher, Mrs. White, just around the corner from our house. If I remember correctly, I despised those lessons. I didn&#x27;t last long doing them. But I (tried to) play guitar now and then until I was 15, and that was when I really started to play. Long story short, I went to see Thin Lizzy in Cork with one of my friends. Thought it was the greatest thing ever. So, I got a Fender Squier electric not long after. I had a bunch of musician friends so we were constantly jamming. At 15 I joined a metal band, and within a few months we were gigging around Cork and Waterford. At 16 or 17 we did a mini-tour around Ireland and some places in Northern Ireland. It was amazing. I wanted to be a rockstar!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;squier.jpg&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
 &lt;figcaption&gt;Fender Squier, pretty much the first electric I had.&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guitar was and still is a massive part of my life, however, long story short, I am not a rockstar. That dream was drowned out by computers in my late teens&#x2F;early twenties. But, I&#x27;m getting ahead of myself. In my last two years of school, I was playing guitar pretty much 8 hours a day. I would come home from school and do nothing but play guitar. I did not study. I did terribly in my leaving cert because of this, causing me to have to repeat maths - a subject which I now absolutely love by the way!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I decided to do a Game Design course while also studying to repeat maths the next summer. My thinking was &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Dude, you love games. You&#x27;ve enjoyed computering in the past. Think about it, those two things together, bliss!&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. I started the course, and within a few weeks I just wanted to drop out. This might have had something to do with my rockstar dream, I was still in that metal band I joined back when I was 15 (I was 18 going on 19 at this point), and this was still at the forefront of my mind. Or perhaps it was the copious amount of alcohol I was consuming at all the partys I was going to at the time. I can&#x27;t seem to remember... I wonder why 🤔.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;linux-and-hacking&quot;&gt;Linux and Hacking&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I dropped out - spoiler alert I did drop out in the end - I was introduced to a bunch of things that set me on my way to where I am now. The first was Linux. I lived with one of the guys on our course and he introduced me to Backtrack Linux. This was the coolest thing I had ever seen. Within a few weeks I was cracking our neighbours WEP based routers, and getting free internet. WEP was a poorly implemented security protocol in use on most wireless routers in the 2000&#x27;s&#x2F;2010&#x27;s. It&#x27;s been a while, but I think the attack involved replaying captured ARP packets, which would cause the target router to have to generate a new IV (Initialization Vector), and then we would capture that and replay, continue until you have enough IV&#x27;s and data to crack the WEP key.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was not a good thing to do. It was a terrible thing to do. But I did it anyway, and I enjoyed it. I was a dumb kid. Regardless of the ethics, it&#x27;s what got me seriously interested in computers. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other thing I was introduced to was Java. This was the coolest thing ever to me at the time. We did Visual Basic, ActionScript (Flash 
😬), and Java in the course. So of course Java was amazing!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;java-in-the-past&quot;&gt;Java in the Past&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quick tangent. As I am writing this I am remembering things that seem to have been lost deep in the darkest corners of my mind. My dad did a masters in Software in around 2003, about the time I was messing with Photoshop. I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; I wrote some code back then. A snake game. I distinctly remember reading a book on Java 2.0 at the very least. Thinking, what is all this, this is cool! Not having a clue what was going on.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;java-is-amazing&quot;&gt;Java is ... Amazing!?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, I bet you&#x27;ve never heard that before. We did Java just after Visual Basic, and our teacher was a Russian woman who had worked in the industry. She taught that class well, as far as I remember, unlike the teacher for the VB class. The fact I could now understand a programming language and write an actual program was exhilarating. No word of a lie there, genuinely exhilarating. I kind of realized I didn&#x27;t care too much about building games after that. I was more interested in programming in general. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;onto-computer-science&quot;&gt;Onto Computer Science&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided, just after the first semester of the Game Design course, that I would prefer to do Computer Science. So, I dropped out of the course overall. I did still repeat maths that year and ended up doing well. Because of that, I could apply for college. I did, and got in and became a CS student! From day one I loved it. Since my friend had introduced me to Linux I had been doing a lot more tinkering with it. I had pretty much all but forgotten about all the security tools on backtrack (I was still using this at the time) and was more interested in how the hell this thing ever turned on. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We didn&#x27;t cover anything to do with Operating Systems in the first year, however. We mostly did PHP. Which probably sounds crazy to you right now. But, it did get me my first job in Software, building a site for the hotel I worked at. It&#x27;s still visible &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;web.archive.org&#x2F;web&#x2F;20110202220118&#x2F;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;walterraleighhotel.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;here at https:&#x2F;&#x2F;web.archive.org&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. This is it, in all its Web 1.0 glory:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;wayofthepie.github.io&#x2F;personal&#x2F;reflecting-on-my-career-to-date&#x2F;walter-raleigh-site.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given modern design and development standards, this isn&#x27;t the best-looking site! But, it was 2010 when I started it. I was a first or second-year college student with no real-world dev experience, and I built this out with PHP and Javascript. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was, and still am, immensely proud of this. I learned a tonne, not only about the technologies I used to implement it but about customer interaction, where that can go wrong. About how hard communication can be, not only across the tech boundary (my manager who asked me to do this had no tech experience and could barely work a computer) but also across the business boundary - why are we building this? What is the business reason? What is the end goal of a new site?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got paid something like €2500 too, which was amazing to me at the time. Saying that, I put in a ridiculous amount of hours, thinking back it was not worth it monetarily. But it was worth it for the learning.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, I kind of flew through the years up to my late teens and early twenties. We are now at about first year or second year in college. I&#x27;ll finish this soon in a follow on post! &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
